<points>
 
 
<point>
<title>Bornholmer Strasse</title>
<title language="DE">Bornholmer Straße</title>
<subtitle>Memories of the Fall</subtitle>
<subtitle  language="DE">Erinnerung an den Mauerfall</subtitle>
<latitude>52.555063</latitude>
<longitude>13.398588</longitude>

<content>In Bornholmer Strasse there are still some scattered remains of the Berlin Wall. Only a few pieces are well preserved. Here you can find an important memorial on the bridge Boesebruecke. There is the plate show on the photo, which reminds the people of the Fall of the Wall.  The border crossing which was located here was the first one which was opened in the night of the Fall of the Wall. </content>

<content language="DE">An der Bornholmer Straße finden sich noch vereinzelte Überreste der Berliner Mauer. Hier sind nur wenige Teile erhalten geblieben. Ein wichtiges Denkmal befindet sich auf der Bösebrücke. Dort erinnert die unten gezeigte Tafel and den Fall der Berliner Mauer 1989. Denn der Grenzübergang der sich hier befand war der Erste der zum Mauerfall geöffnet wurde.</content>

<image>boesebrucke.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Exxu</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>PublicDomain</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:BoeseBrueckeTafel.png</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 


<point>
<title>Bernauer Strasse</title>
<title language="DE">Bernauer Straße</title>
<subtitle>Longest Remaining Segment</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Längster erhaltener Abschnitt</subtitle>
<latitude>52.536661</latitude>
<longitude>13.391923</longitude>

<content>In Bernauer Strasse there is one of the longest remaining (still original) segments of the Berlin Wall. It is discontinued by several gaps, but it still shows the huge area which was occupied by the Wall in the past. Additonally the memorial place "Berlin Wall" was established here. The picture below shows the  strap of the Berlin Wall", which is still well recognizable today.</content>

<content language="DE">In der Bernauer Straße steht einer der längsten noch original erhaltenen Abschnitte der Mauer. Dieser ist zwar durch größere Lücken unterbrochen, zeigt aber immernoch welche Fläche der Mauerstreifen früher eingenommen hat. Zudem wurde hier die Gedenkstätte "Berliner Mauer" errichtet. Das Bild unten zeigt den heute immernoch sehr deutlich erkennbaren Mauerstreifen.</content>

<image>bernauer.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Franz Richter</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Bernauer_Stra%C3%9Fe_1920.jpg?uselang=de</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 


<point>
<title>Mauerpark</title>
<subtitle>Park with Flea Market and Wall Ruins</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Park mit Flohmarkt und Mauerresten</subtitle>
<longitude>13.403690</longitude>
<latitude>52.543447</latitude>

<content>The Mauerpark is today a very famous place for recreation in the district "Prenzlauer Berg". Here is a great flea market, which occurs normally on every weekend. Here you can find a mass of interssting objects out of the Berlin history. On an elevation next to the park there area pieces of the remaining Wall, which are still well-preserved. Behind the Wall you can find the Max-Schmeling-Hall and the Friedrich-Ludwig-Jahn sport area.</content>

<content language="DE">Der Mauerpark ist heute ein beliebter Erholungsort im Stadtteil "Prenzlauer Berg". Hier findet am Wochenende ein großer Flohmarkt statt, auf dem viele interessante Artikel zu finden sind. Auf einer Erhöhung befinden sich die Mauerreste, die überwiegend sehr gut erhalten sind. Dahinter liegt die Max-Schmeling-Halle und der Friedrich-Ludwig-Jahn-Sportpark.</content>

<image>mauerpark.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Franz Richter</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mauerpark_1979.jpg</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 


<point>
<title>Gartenstrasse</title>
<title language="DE">Gartenstraße</title>
<subtitle>The Cobblestone shows the Course</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Pflastersteine zeigen den Verlauf</subtitle>
<latitude>52.536654</latitude>
<longitude>13.383348</longitude>

<content>In the Gartenstrasse you can find sporadical leftovers of the Berlin Wall. In the areas where there is no Wall anymore the cobblestones are showing the original course of the Berlin Wall.</content>

<content language="DE">In der Gartenstraße finden sich noch weitere vereinzelte Reste der Hinterlandmauer. Dort wo keine Reste mehr zu finden sind, ist der Verlauf der Mauer mit Pflastersteinen markiert.</content>

<image>gartenstrasse.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Jotquadrat</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Graffito_Berlin_PaNBf_Jaani.jpg</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 




<point>
<title>Niederkirchner Straße</title>
<title language="DE">Niederkirchner Strasse</title>
<subtitle>Long Segment with Memorial</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Langer Abschnitt mit Mauerdenkmal</subtitle>
<latitude>52.507043</latitude>
<longitude>13.382827</longitude>

<content>Another long segment of the Wall can be found in the Niederkirchner Straße. This section is only a few walking minutes away from the Potsdamer Platz. Here you can find the exhibition area and memorial "Topography of Terror". Since 1990 this section is under preservation order. The image below shows the sign of the memorial.</content>

<content language="DE">Ein ebenfalls langer Abschnitt findet sich in der Niederkirchner Straße. Dieser Abschnitt ist nur wenige Gehminuten vom Potsdamer Platz entfernt. Hier findet sich das Ausstellungsgelände "Topographie des Terrors". Dieser Abschnitt der Mauer wurde 1990 unter Denkmalschutz gestellt. Das Bild unten zeigt einen Abschnitt der Mauer inklusive des Schildes zum Mauerdenkmal.</content>

<image>niederkirchner.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Manfred Brückels</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Berliner_Mauer,_Baudenkmal.jpg?uselang=de</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 




<point>
<title>St. Hedwigs Cemetery</title>
<title language="DE">St. Hedwigs Friedhof</title>
<subtitle>Cemetery with Wall Ruins</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Friedhof mit Mauerresten</subtitle>
<latitude>52.538889</latitude>
<longitude>13.376944</longitude>

<content>Along the entire Liesenstrasse and particulary on the St. Hedwigs Cemetery there are a lot of existing, well-preserved Wall ruins. A lot of these pieces are under preservation order. The St.Hedwig Cemetery furthermore is the oldest cath zudem der älteste Catholic Cementery in Berlin. The picture shows a segement of the Wall at the Liesenbruecken.</content>

<content language="DE">Entlang der gesamten Liesenstraße und vor allem auf dem Friedhof St.Hedwig existieren auch heute noch viele Mauerreste und Grenzanlagen. Viele dieser Teile stehen unter Denkmalschutz. Der St.Hedwigs Friedhof ist zudem der älteste katholische Friedhof Berlins. Das Bild zeigt einen Teil der Mauerreste and den Liesenbrücken.</content>

<image>liesenstrasse.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Beek100</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>GNU License</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Liesenstra%C3%9Fe,_Mauerrest_02.jpg?uselang=de</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 



<point>
<title>East-Side-Gallery</title>
<subtitle>Over 100 Wall Paintings</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Über 100 Mauergemälde</subtitle>
<latitude>52.505113</latitude>
<longitude>13.439424</longitude>

<content>The East-Side-Gallery is a 1316 meter (1439 yards) long segement of the Berlin Wall, which was painted by 118 different artists from all over the world. The East-Side-Gallery was established in September 1990. The East-Side-Gallery is the longest open air gallery in the world. Over the years a lot of paintings got weathered, but they are renovated regulary through different initatives.</content>

<content language="DE">Die East-Side-Gallery ist ein 1316m langes Stück der Hintelandmauer auf der sich 118 Künstler aus aller Welt mit ihren Gemälden verewigt haben. Die East-Side-Gallery wurde im September 1990 eröffnet. Die East-Side-Gallery ist damit die längste Open-Air-Galerie der Welt. Im Laufe der Jahre sind viele der Bilder vewittert, werden aber durch verschiedene Initiativen regelmäßig saniert.</content>

<image>eastsidegallery.jpg</image>
<imagecr>FreedomWizard</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:FW_Berliner_Mauer.JPG?uselang=de</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 



<point>
<title>Potsdamer Platz</title>
<subtitle>The Famous Wall Pieces</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Die bekanntesten Mauerteile</subtitle>
<latitude>52.508747</latitude>
<longitude>13.376642</longitude>

<content>The Wall ruins at Potsdamer Platz area the most famous remaining pieves of the Wall today. It is interessting that the Potsdamer Platz is the only location in Berlin which shows the course of the inner and the outer Wall (indicated by cobblestones). Here you can meet some street performers, that are dressed in original uniformes and which you can ask to take a Wall-picture together with them.</content>

<content language="DE">Die Mauerteile am Potsdamer Platz gehören zu den bekanntesten noch übrigen Teilen. Interessant ist, dass als einziges am Potsdamer Platz der Verlauf der inneren Mauer als auch der äußeren Mauer mit Pflastersteinen markiert wurde. Hier trifft man regelmäßig auf Straßenkünstler mit Original-Uniformen, mit den man gemeinsam ein Mauer-Foto schießen kann.</content>

<image>potsdamerplatz.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Marcela</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>GNU License</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Berlin-zentrum-by-RalfR-021.jpg</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point> 



<point>
<title>Checkpoint Charlie</title>
<subtitle>Replicated Border Crossing</subtitle>
<subtitle language="DE">Nachgestellter Grenzübergang</subtitle>

<content>Today Checkpoint Charlie is still one of the most famous sights in Berlin. Here you can find a replicated of the original coulisse, which includes a small barrack and a sign that shows that you are leaving the particular sector (American oder Soviet). Additionally, there is the Checkpoint Charlie Museum, which was established in a building next to the checkpoint. Here you can get some insights into the history of the Berlin Wall.</content>

<content language="DE">Auch heute noch zählt Checkpoint Charlie zu den wichtigsten Sehenswürdikeiten in Berlin. Hier wurde eine Rekonstruktion der ursprünglichen Kulisse geschaffen inklusive einer einer kleinen Baracke und einem Schild mit der Information, dass man nun den jeweiligen Sektor verlässt. Zudem wurde hier das Checkpoint Charlie Museum errichtet in welchem man sich über die vergangene Zeit informieren kann.</content>

<longitude>13.390296</longitude>
<latitude>52.507679</latitude>

<image>checkpointheute.jpg</image>
<imagecr>Norbert Aepli</imagecr>
<imagecrtype>CreativeCommons</imagecrtype>
<imagecrurl>http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Checkpoint_Charlie_2005_072.JPG</imagecrurl>

<type>3</type>
</point>

</points>